Guide to the George H. Bauer Jean Paul Sartre Manuscript Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George H. Bauer Jean Paul Sartre manuscript collection
1945-1962
GEN MSS 505
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.05
(3 boxes)
A collection of materials by Sartre acquired by George H. Bauer. The majority of the material consists of drafts for individual works in Sartre's series of novels collectively titled "Chemins de la liberté": a holograph and typescript draft of "La mort dans l'âme" and holograph draft pages of "La dernière chance", which contains a section titled "Drôle d'amitié" (which appeared in the journal, "Les Temps Modernes".) Also included are draft pages of essays on Jean Genet, Gjon Mili, a 1947 election, and other subjects, as well as a drawing titled "C'est mon amour aux Baux", and several letters: Fernando Gerassi to George H. Bauer (1962 Jul 28); a draft of a letter [by Sartre?] to an unidentified recipient; Les Éditions Nagel to Jean Cau (1949 Nov 16, on verso of a draft page); Comité français d'échanges avec L'Allemagne Nouvelle to Sartre (1948 Nov 20); and Les Éditions Nagel to Sartre (1948 Nov 16), these last two letters filed with the drafts of "La mort dansl'âme".
Bauer, George Howard, 1933-
Sartre, Jean-Paul, 1905-1980
Sartre, Jean-Paul, 1905-1980 ( Chemins de la liberté)
Sartre, Jean-Paul, 1905-1980 ( Chemins de la liberté, 4, Dernière chance)
Sartre, Jean-Paul, 1905-1980 ( Chemins de la liberté, 3, Mort dans l'âme)
Comité français d'échanges avec l'Allemagne nouvelle
Nagel Publishers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Ellen W. Bauer on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2001.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Other Sartre material is cataloged in the Jean Paul Sartre Collection, GEN MSS 143.
Jean Paul Sartre
Jean Paul Sartre (1905-1980), existentialist philosopher, dramatist and novelist, author of La Nausée (1938), Huis clos (1943), and L'être et le néant (1943).
George H. Bauer
George H. Bauer (1933-1996), author of two books on Sartre: Sartre and the Artist (1969) and Les Oeuvres romanesques de Jean-Paul Sartre (1983). He was born in Cortez, California, and was educated at the University of Colorado (A.B. 1955) and Indiana University (M.A. 1960, Ph.D. 1967). After serving in U.S. Army Military Intelligence in 1956-58, he taught French and comparative literature at Dartmouth College, Northwestern University, and the University of Minnesota before attaining a full professorship at the University of Southern California, Los Angeles, in 1977. He married Ellen Wood in 1962; the couple had two children.
Scope and Contents
A collection of materials by Sartre acquired by George H. Bauer. The majority of the material consists of drafts for individual works in Sartre's series of novels collectively titled "Chemins de la liberté": a holograph and typescript draft of "La mort dans l'âme" and holograph draft pages of "La dernière chance", which contains a section titled "Drôle d'amitié" (which appeared in the journal, "Les Temps Modernes".) Also included are draft pages of essays on Jean Genet, Gjon Mili, a 1947 election, and other subjects, as well as a drawing titled "C'est mon amour aux Baux", and several letters: Fernando Gerassi to George H. Bauer (1962 Jul 28); a draft of a letter [by Sartre?] to an unidentified recipient; Les Éditions Nagel to Jean Cau (1949 Nov 16, on verso of a draft page); Comité français d'échanges avec L'Allemagne Nouvelle to Sartre (1948 Nov 20); and Les Éditions Nagel to Sartre (1948 Nov 16), these last two letters filed with the drafts of "La mort dansl'âme".
Authors, French -- 20th Century -- Archives; Bauer, George Howard, 1933-; Sartre, Jean-Paul, 1905-1980; Gerassi, Fernando
- La Mort dans L'âme
  - Draft, holograph and typescript, corrected, ca. 1945-46 (Box 1, Folder 1-13)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes: letter from Comité français d'échanges avec L'Allemagne Nouvelle to Sartre, 1948 Nov 20; and letter from Les Éditions Nagel to Sartre, 1948 Nov 16
  - Original binders, ca. 1945-46 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
- La Dernière Chance
  - Draft pages, ca. 1947-49 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Draft pages, ca. 1947-49 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Draft pages, ca. 1947-49 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Draft, notebook, of section published as "Drôle d'amitié, ca. 1947-49 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Draft pages, ca. 1947-49 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Draft pages, ca. 1947-49 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Draft fragments, variants of first page, ca. 1947-49 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Miscellaneous manuscript pages and letters
  - Letter: Fernando Gerassi to George H. Bauer, 1962 Jul 28 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Draft of letter: [Sartre?] to unidentified recipient, ca. 1948 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Drawing: "C'est mon amour aux Baux", 1945 Aug 3 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Draft pages re: election of 1947, ca. 1947 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Draft pages re: Jean Genet, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Draft pages re: Gjon Mili, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Drafts pages and notes on various subjects, ca. 1947-49 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    One page of notes is on the verso of a letter from Les Éditions Nagel to Jean Cau, 1949 Nov 16